Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Thompson Way/Thompson Total Branding records, approximately 1975-2000 and undated RL.11328
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Thompson Way/Thompson Total Branding records
approximately 1975-2000 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
RL.11328
6.0 Linear Feet
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. It is headquartered in New York. Collection consists of training and policy manuals, presentations, other printed materials and videocassettes pertaining to the T-Plan, Thompson Way and Thompson Total Branding programs. Materials appear in English, Spanish and Japanese and include materials from JWT offices in The U.S., Argentina, Australia, Canada, India, Italy, Japan, Mexico and Thailand. Case study information for individual companies include DeBeers, Ford, Nabisco (Ritz crackers), Nabob Coffee, Nestle, Steppenwolf Theater and White Castle. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Thompson Way; Thompson Total Branding; Audiovisual Materials.
Biographical / Historical
JWT's advertising reputation was historically based on a systematic approach to account planning and management. Beginning around 1916, JWT developed a simple mnemonic called the T-Square, a printed or metal draftsman's t-square that bore five key questions to guide account strategy. In the 1920s, account planning was further systematized with the Plan and Data Form, which considered the market situation, consumer base and advertising strategy. During the 1960s the London Office developed what came to be known as the T-Plan. The T-Plan began with a situation analysis that took into account not only the position of the product in the market, but also that of competing products, and undertook a much finer-grained analysis of the consumer base. This information drove actions by two different parties within JWT: the Target Planning Team working on the account, and the Strategy Review Board, a management oversight committee who reviewed and made recommendations on how a campaign should progress. The Thompson Way was launched in 1987, a set of account management tools intended to reinforce JWT's core mission of the time "to deliver greater value from their advertising than any other agency." In 1996, a new version, called Thompson Total Branding, emerged, that incorporated market assessments, product positioning, target audience and brand vision into a comprehensive and integrated brand communications strategy. Thompson Total Branding also sought to reposition the entire agency in terms of global brand communications. The following year, 1997, JWT launched Thompson Total Targeting, which integrated brand communications with marketing database analysis.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Thompson Way/Thompson Total Branding records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1993-2002.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following J. Walter Thompson Company Archives collections held in the Hartman Center:
Account Files; Chicago Office records; Newsletter collection; Peter Schweitzer papers; Publications.
Collection Overview
Consists of training and policy manuals, presentation materials, other printed materials and videocassettes pertaining to the T-Plan, Thompson Way and Thompson Total Branding programs. Materials appear in English, Spanish and Japanese and include materials from JWT offices in The U.S., Argentina, Australia, Canada, India, Italy, Japan, Mexico and Thailand. Case study information for individual companies include DeBeers, Ford, Nabisco (Ritz crackers), Nabob Coffee, Nestle, Steppenwolf Theater and White Castle. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Advertising -- Management; Advertising -- History; Advertising -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Advertising agencies; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
- Thompson Way, approximately 1975-1996 and undated; 1
  - A guide to the JWT T-Plan, approximately 1975 (Box 1)
  - Advertising Planning Methods, 1987-1996; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Advertising Process and Procedures, 1995 (Box 1)
  - El Manuel Para Cuentos de JWT (Spanish version of JWT Account Manager's Handbook), 1989 (Box 1)
  - Expanded Thompson Way Program, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Japan--Account Managers Handbook (in Japanese), undated (Box 1)
  - Japan--JWT Guide to Research (in Japanese), 1992 (Box 1)
  - Japan--JWT Media Person's Handbook (in Japanese), 1992 (Box 2)
  - JWT Account Manager's Handbook, 1990 (Box 2)
  - JWT Director-in-charge: Roles and Expectations, 1993 (Box 2)
  - JWT Guide to Research, 1993 (Box 2)
  - JWT Media Person's Handbook, 1989 (Box 2)
  - JWT New Business Checklist for Winners, 1992 (Box 2)
  - JWT New Business Handbook, 1991 (Box 2)
  - JWT Office Managers' Development Program "Swap Shop", 1992 (Box 2)
  - JWT Office Managers' Development Program "Swap Shop", 1992 (Box 3)
  - La Guia para Investigacion de JWT (Spanish version of JWT Guide to Research), 1990 (Box 3)
  - Selling the Most Effective, Distinctive Advertising in the Marketplace, 1991; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Spring Training '92: Better Together, 1992; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Thompson Account Managers' Handbook, undated (Box 3)
  - Thompson Account Managers' Handbook, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Thompson Way, undated (Box 4)
  - Thompson Way graduate recruitment (London), 1996 (Box 4)
  - Thompson Way Handbook, 1990 (Box 4)
  - What Others Really Think About Account Managers, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous binders for exhibits, undated (Box 9)
- Thompson Total Branding (TTB), 1991-2001 and undated; 2
  - Argentina--Training program, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Bangkok--Total Branding X-Files package "They Don't Do It Like This at Any Other Agency", 1996 (Box 8)
  - Canada--A Successful Quest for Total Branding: J. Walter Thompson Canada and Nabob (Coffee) 1997-1998 (Box 10)
  - Europe--Introductory presentation, 1996; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Europe--Pre-release version, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Ford--No Boundaries Total Branding plan, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Hindustan Thompson--All-India TTB introduction, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Hindustan Thompson--Say Hello to Thompson Total Branding, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Japan--TTB introducing package, 1996 (Box 5)
  - London--Core team meeting, 1997 (Box 5)
  - London--Thompson Way of Total Branding, 1996; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - London--Total Branding: The Branding Idea, 1999 (Box 5)
  - London--TTB overview presentation, 1997 (Box 5)
  - Melbourne--TTB handbook, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Melbourne--X-Files presentation, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Mexico--TTB meeting "Transformation" binder, undated (Box 6)
  - Milan--TTB introduction slides, approximately 1996 (Box 6)
  - Mumbai--Contract/Branding TTB introduction, 1995-1996 (Box 6)
  - Mumbai--TTB workshop notepad, undated (Box 6)
  - Nestle conference, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Nestle/Sao Paulo--The War of the Milk Modifiers, 1993-1995; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Our Best Total Branding, 1999 (Box 6)
  - Our New Management Vision, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Pre-launch planning meeting, 1996 (Box 7)
  - Pre-release version, 1996 (Box 7)
  - Ritz Crackers TTB awards (Chicago), 2000 (Box 7)
  - Software rollout, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Steppenwolf Theater Company--Thompson Total Branding Program, JWT Chicago, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Thompson Total Branding workshop, 1999 (Box 7)
  - Thompson Way of Total Branding examples, 1996 (Box 7)
  - Total Branding brochure, undated (Box 7)
  - Total Branding glossary, 1996 (Box 7)
  - White Castle case study, 1996 (Box 7)
  - Total Branding T-shirt, undated (Box 7)
  - Total Branding Workshop (Mumbai) polo shirt, 1996 (Box 7)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1996-2001 and undated; 3
  - Pre Release Version The Thompson Way of Total Branding, 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11328-Umatic-001)
    Scope and Contents
    Television commercials for TTB case histories: Ford F0150 "Canyon", "Working Harder/Toughness"; ESSO :Nightwatch"; Oscar Mayer "Talent Search/Superbowl"; Nutri-Grain "Engine Room"; USMC "Transformation"; California Lottery "Kitchen Window", "Fish"; Lux "Airport"; Aguila Beer "Beach Party"; Sprint Sense "Just a Dime"; Heineken (Switzerland) total communications video case study
  - Ritz crackers television spots, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11328-Umatic-002)
    Bed, Bell, Snowman, Football, Soup, Peanut Butter, On the Go, Conga
  - Rock Video on Total Branding, 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11328-Umatic-003)
    JWT in-house video, Kuala Lampur Malaysia. 8:00
  - Thompson Total Branding Award, Advertising TV, 1998 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11328-Umatic-004)
  - Thompson Total Branding Award, Case History Video, 1998 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11328-Umatic-005)
  - Total Branding Launch JWT Milan (NTSC), 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11328-Umatic-006)
  - Case Nescau case study (Brazil), undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11328-VHS-001)
    Sixteen television spots; NTSC.
  - Thompson Total Branding Parts 1 and 2, 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11328-VHS-002)
    Client material includes De Beers, Motorola, Gerber Baby, White Castle, Midas, Marine Corps, Philly Cheese, Oscar Mayer, Nutri-Grain, Radio 3 Amsterdam, Andrex/Scott Paper, Sprint, John Cleese
  - Thompson Total Branding X-Files Presentation (Melbourne), 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11328-VHS-003)
  - Total Branding Video, 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11328-VHS-004)
    For Internal Use Only, Workshops and presentations (John Furr)
  - Bangkok--Total Branding X-Files package "They Don't Do It Like This at Any Other Agency", 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11328-OP-005)
  - Ford No Boundaries (PAL), undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11328-Bcam-001)
  - TTB Advertising Radio: Nabob Coffee, undated (Box AV1, Audio-cassette RL11328-CS-001)
  - Bangkok--Total Branding X-Files package "They Don't Do It Like This at Any Other Agency", 1996 (Box AV1, Audio-cassette RL11328-CS-002)
  - Forever M De Beers Global, Millennium Campaign presentation, undated (Box AV1, Video-disc RL11328-OP-001)
  - Ritz crackers Powerpoint presentation, undated (Box AV1, Video-disc RL11328-OP-002)
  - Successful Quest for Total Branding: J. Walter Thompson Canada and Nabob Coffee 1997-1998 (Box AV1, Video-disc RL11328-OP-003)
  - Thompson Total Branding Awards winners, 2000 (Box AV1, Video-disc RL11328-OP-004)
  - TTB 2001 Awards Highly Commended (Box AV1, Video-disc RL11328-OP-005)